<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/changes/1.0.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/changes/1.0.0 ./changes.xsd">
	<properties>
		<author>James Agnew</author>
		<title>HAPI FHIR Changelog</title>
	</properties>
	<body>
		<release version="0.7" date="TBD">
			<action type="add" dev="suranga">
				Documentation fixes
			</action>			
			<action type="add" dev="dougmartin">
				Add a collection of new methods on the generic client which support the
				<![CDATA[ 
				<b><a href="./apidocs/ca/uhn/fhir/rest/client/IGenericClient.html#read(java.lang.Class,%20ca.uhn.fhir.model.primitive.UriDt)">read</a></b>,
				<b><a href="./apidocs/ca/uhn/fhir/rest/client/IGenericClient.html#vread(java.lang.Class,%20ca.uhn.fhir.model.primitive.UriDt)">read</a></b>,
				and <b><a href="./apidocs/ca/uhn/fhir/rest/client/IGenericClient.html#search(java.lang.Class,%20ca.uhn.fhir.model.primitive.UriDt)">search</a></b>
				]]>
				operations using an absolute URL. This allows developers to perform these operations using
				URLs they obtained from other sources (or external resource references within resources). In
				addition, the existing read/vread operations will now access absolute URL references if
				they are passed in. Thanks to Doug Martin of the Regenstrief Center for Biomedical Informatics
				for contributing this implementation!
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Server implementation was not correctly figuring out its own FHIR Base URL when deployed
				on Amazon Web Service server. Thanks to Jeffrey Ting and Bill De Beaubien of
				Systems Made Simple for their help in figuring out this issue! 
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				XML Parser failed to encode fields with both a resource reference child and
				a primitive type child. Thanks to Jeffrey Ting and Bill De Beaubien of
				Systems Made Simple for their help in figuring out this issue!
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				HAPI now runs successfully on Servlet 2.5 containers (such as Tomcat 6). Thanks to
				Bernard Gitaadji for reporting and diagnosing the issue!
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Summary (in the bundle entry) is now encoded by the XML and JSON parsers if supplied. Thanks to David Hay of 
				Orion Health for reporting this!
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="24">
				Conformance profiles which are automatically generated by the server were missing a few mandatory elements,
				which meant that the profile did not correctly validate. Thanks to Bill de Beaubien of Systems Made Simple
				for reporting this!				
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				XHTML (in narratives) containing escapable characters (e.g. &lt; or &quot;) will now always have those characters 
				escaped properly in encoded messages.
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Resources containing entities which are not valid in basic XML (e.g. &amp;sect;) will have those
				entities converted to their equivalent unicode characters when resources are encoded, since FHIR does
				not allow extended entities in resource instances.
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Add a new client interceptor which adds HTTP Authorization Bearer Tokens (for use with OAUTH2 servers)
				to client requests.
			</action>			
			<action type="fix">
				Add phloc-commons dependency explicitly, which resolves an issue building HAPI from source on
				some platforms. Thanks to Odysseas Pentakalos for the patch!
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				HAPI now logs a single line indicating the StAX implementation being used upon the
				first time an XML parser is created.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="26" dev="akley">
				HAPI now logs a single line indicating the StAX implementation being used upon the
				first time an XML parser is created.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="0.6" date="2014-Sep-08" description="This release brings a number of new features and bug fixes!">
			<!-- 
			<action type="add">
				Allow generic client  ... OAUTH
			</action>
			-->
			<action type="add">
				Add server interceptor framework, and new interceptor for logging incoming
				requests.   
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Add server validation framework for validating resources against the FHIR schemas and schematrons
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Tester UI created double _format and _pretty param entries in searches. Thanks to Gered King of University
				Health Network for reporting!   
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="4">
				Create method was incorrectly returning an HTTP 204 on sucessful completion, but
				should be returning an HTTP 200 per the FHIR specification. Thanks to wanghaisheng 
				for reporting! 
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				FHIR Tester UI now correctly sends UTF-8 charset in responses so that message payloads containing
				non US-ASCII characters will correctly display in the browser
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				JSON parser was incorrectly encoding extensions on composite elements outside the element itself
				(as is done correctly for non-composite elements) instead of inside of them. Thanks to David Hay of
				Orion for reporting this!
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Contained/included resource instances received by a client are now automatically 
				added to any ResourceReferenceDt instancea in other resources which reference them.
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Add documentation on how to use eBay CORS Filter to support Cross Origin Resource
				Sharing (CORS) to server. CORS support that was built in to the server itself has
				been removed, as it did not work correctly (and was reinventing a wheel that others
				have done a great job inventing). Thanks to Peter Bernhardt of Relay Health for all the assistance
				in testing this!
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				IResource interface did not expose the getLanguage/setLanguage methods from BaseResource,
				so the resource language was difficult to access.
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				JSON Parser now gives a more friendly error message if it tries to parse JSON with invalid use 
				of single quotes
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Transaction server method is now allowed to return an OperationOutcome in addition to the
				incoming resources. The public test server now does this in order to return status information
				about the transaction processing.
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Update method in the server can now flag (via a field on the MethodOutcome object being returned)
				that the result was actually a creation, and Create method can indicate that it was actually an
				update. This has no effect other than to switch between the HTTP 200 and HTTP 201 status codes on the
				response, but this may be useful in some circumstances.
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Annotation client search methods with a specific resource type (e.g. List&lt;Patient&gt; search())
				won't return any resources that aren't of the correct type that are received in a response
				bundle (generally these are referenced resources, so they are populated in the reference fields instead).
				Thanks to Tahura Chaudhry of University Health Network for the unit test!
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Added narrative generator template for OperationOutcome resource
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Date/time types did not correctly parse values in the format "yyyymmdd" (although the FHIR-defined format
				is "yyyy-mm-dd" anyhow, and this is correctly handled). Thanks to Jeffrey Ting of Systems Made Simple
				for reporting! 
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Server search method for an unnamed query gets called if the client requests a named query
				with the same parameter list. Thanks to Neal Acharya of University Health Network for reporting!			
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Category header (for tags) is correctly read in client for "read" operation
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Transaction method in server can now have parameter type Bundle instead of
				List&lt;IResource&gt;
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				HAPI parsers now use field access to get/set values instead of method accessors and mutators.
				This should give a small performance boost.
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				JSON parser encodes resource references incorrectly, using the name "resource" instead
				of the name "reference" for the actual reference. Thanks to
				Ricky Nguyen for reporting and tracking down the issue!
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Rename NotImpementedException to NotImplementedException (to correct typo)
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Server setUseBrowserFriendlyContentType setting also respected for errors (e.g. OperationOutcome with 4xx/5xx status)
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Fix performance issue in date/time datatypes where pattern matchers were not static
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Server now gives a more helpful error message if a @Read method has a search parameter (which is invalid, but
				previously lead to a very unhelpful error message). Thanks to Tahura Chaudhry of UHN for reporting!
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Resource of type "List" failed to parse from a bundle correctly. Thanks to David Hay of Orion Health 
				for reporting!
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				QuantityParam correctly encodes approximate (~) prefix to values
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="14">
				If a server defines a method with parameter "_id", incoming search requests for that method may
				get delegated to the wrong method. Thanks to Neal Acharya for reporting! 
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				SecurityEvent.Object structural element has been renamed to 
				SecurityEvent.ObjectElement to avoid conflicting names with the 
				java Object class. Thanks to Laurie Macdougall-Sookraj of UHN for
				reporting! 
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Text/narrative blocks that were created with a non-empty
				namespace prefix (e.g. &lt;xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="..."&gt;...&lt;/xhtml:div&gt;)
				failed to encode correctly (prefix was missing in encoded resource)				
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Resource references previously encoded their children (display and reference)
				in the wrong order so references with both would fail schema validation.
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				SecurityEvent resource's enums now use friendly enum names instead of the unfriendly
				numeric code values. Thanks to Laurie MacDougall-Sookraj of UHN for the
				suggestion!
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="0.5" date="2014-Jul-30">
			<action type="add">
				HAPI has a number of RESTful method parameter types that have similar but not identical
				purposes and confusing names. A cleanup has been undertaken to clean this up.
				This means that a number of existing classes
				have been deprocated in favour of new naming schemes.
				<![CDATA[<br/><br/>]]>
				All annotation-based clients and all server search method parameters are now named
				(type)Param, for example: StringParam, TokenParam, etc.
				<![CDATA[<br/><br/>]]>
				All generic/fluent client method parameters are now named
				(type)ClientParam, for example: StringClientParam, TokenClientParam, etc.
				<![CDATA[<br/><br/>]]>
				All renamed classes have been retained and deprocated, so this change should not cause any issues
				for existing applications but those applications should be refactored to use the 
				new parameters when possible.
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Allow server methods to return wildcard generic types (e.g. List&lt;? extends IResource&gt;)
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Search parameters are not properly escaped and unescaped. E.g. for a token parameter such as
				"&amp;identifier=system|codepart1\|codepart2"
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Add support for OPTIONS verb (which returns the server conformance statement)
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Add support for CORS headers in server
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Bump SLF4j dependency to latest version (1.7.7)
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Add interceptor framework for clients (annotation based and generic), and add interceptors
				for configurable logging, capturing requests and responses, and HTTP basic auth.
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Transaction client invocations with XML encoding were using the wrong content type ("application/xml+fhir" instead 
				of the correct "application/atom+xml"). Thanks to David Hay of Orion Health for surfacing this one!
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Bundle entries now support a link type of "search". Thanks to David Hay for the suggestion!
			</action>
			<action type="add" issue="1">
				 If a client receives a non 2xx response (e.g. HTTP 500) and the response body is a text/plain message or
				 an OperationOutcome resource, include the message in the exception message so that it will be 
				 more conveniently displayed in logs and other places. Thanks to Neal Acharya for the suggestion! 
			</action>
			<action type="add" issue="2">
				 Read invocations in the client now process the "Content-Location" header and use it to 
				 populate the ID of the returned resource. Thanks to Neal Acharya for the suggestion!
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="3">
				Fix issue where vread invocations on server incorrectly get routed to instance history method if one is 
				defined. Thanks to Neal Acharya from UHN for surfacing this one! 
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Binary reads on a server not include the Content-Disposition header, to prevent HTML in binary 
				blobs from being used for nefarious purposes. See
				<![CDATA[<a href="http://gforge.hl7.org/gf/project/fhir/tracker/?action=TrackerItemEdit&tracker_id=677&tracker_item_id=3298">FHIR Tracker Bug 3298</a>]]>
				for more information.
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Support has been added for using an HTTP proxy for outgoing requests.
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Fix: Primitive extensions declared against custom resource types 
				are encoded even if they have no value. Thanks to David Hay of Orion for
				reporting this!
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Fix: RESTful server deployed to a location where the URL to access it contained a
				space (e.g. a WAR file with a space in the name) failed to work correctly.
				Thanks to David Hay of Orion for reporting this!
			</action>
        </release>			
		<release version="0.4" date="2014-Jul-13">
			<action type="add">
				<![CDATA[<b>BREAKING CHANGE:</b>]]>: IdDt has been modified so that it 
				contains a partial or complete resource identity. Previously it contained
				only the simple alphanumeric id of the resource (the part at the end of the "read" URL for
				that resource) but it can now contain a complete URL or even a partial URL (e.g. "Patient/123")
				and can optionally contain a version (e.g. "Patient/123/_history/456"). New methods have
				been added to this datatype which provide just the numeric portion. See the JavaDoc
				for more information. 
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				<![CDATA[<b>API CHANGE:</b>]]>: Most elements in the HAPI FHIR model contain
				a getId() and setId() method. This method is confusing because it is only actually used
				for IDREF elements (which are rare) but its name makes it easy to confuse with more
				important identifiers. For this reason, these methods have been deprocated and replaced with
				get/setElementSpecificId() methods. The old methods will be removed at some point. Resource
				types are unchanged and retain their get/setId methods.
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Allow use of QuantityDt as a service parameter to support the "quantity" type. Previously
				QuantityDt did not implement IQueryParameterType so it was not valid, and there was no way to
				support quantity search parameters on the server (e.g. Observation.value-quantity)
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Introduce StringParameter type which can be used as a RESTful operation search parameter
				type. StringParameter allows ":exact" matches to be specified in clients, and handled in servers.
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Parsers (XML/JSON) now support deleted entries in bundles
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Transaction method now supported in servers
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Support for Binary resources added (in servers, clients, parsers, etc.)
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Support for Query resources fixed (in parser)
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Nested contained resources (e.g. encoding a resource with a contained resource that itself contains a resource)
				now parse and encode correctly, meaning that all contained resources are placed in the "contained" element
				of the root resource, and the parser looks in the root resource for all container levels when stitching
				contained resources back together.
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Server methods with @Include parameter would sometimes fail when no _include was actually
				specified in query strings.
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Client requests for IdentifierDt types (such as Patient.identifier) did not create the correct
				query string if the system is null.
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Add support for paging responses from RESTful servers.
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Don't fail on narrative blocks in JSON resources with only an XML declaration but no content (these are
				produced by the Health Intersections server) 
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Server now automatically compresses responses if the client indicates support 
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Server failed to support optional parameters when type is String and :exact qualifier is used 
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Read method in client correctly populated resource ID in returned object 
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Support added for deleted-entry by/name, by/email, and comment from Tombstones spec
			</action>
        </release>			
		<release version="0.3" date="2014-May-12" description="This release corrects lots of bugs and introduces the fluent client mode">
        </release>			
	</body>
</document>
