<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/changes/1.0.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/changes/1.0.0 ./changes.xsd">
	<properties>
		<author>James Agnew</author>
		<title>HAPI FHIR Changelog</title>
	</properties>
	<body>
		<release version="0.3" date="2014-May-12" description="This release corrects lots of bugs and introduces the fluent client mode">
        </release>			
		<release version="0.4" date="2014-Jul-13">
			<action type="add">
				<![CDATA[<b>BREAKING CHANGE:</b>]]>: IdDt has been modified so that it 
				contains a partial or complete resource identity. Previously it contained
				only the simple alphanumeric id of the resource (the part at the end of the "read" URL for
				that resource) but it can now contain a complete URL or even a partial URL (e.g. "Patient/123")
				and can optionally contain a version (e.g. "Patient/123/_history/456"). New methods have
				been added to this datatype which provide just the numeric portion. See the JavaDoc
				for more information. 
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				<![CDATA[<b>API CHANGE:</b>]]>: Most elements in the HAPI FHIR model contain
				a getId() and setId() method. This method is confusing because it is only actually used
				for IDREF elements (which are rare) but its name makes it easy to confuse with more
				important identifiers. For this reason, these methods have been deprocated and replaced with
				get/setElementSpecificId() methods. The old methods will be removed at some point. Resource
				types are unchanged and retain their get/setId methods.
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Allow use of QuantityDt as a service parameter to support the "quantity" type. Previously
				QuantityDt did not implement IQueryParameterType so it was not valid, and there was no way to
				support quantity search parameters on the server (e.g. Observation.value-quantity)
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Introduce StringParameter type which can be used as a RESTful operation search parameter
				type. StringParameter allows ":exact" matches to be specified in clients, and handled in servers.
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Parsers (XML/JSON) now support deleted entries in bundles
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Transaction method now supported in servers
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Support for Binary resources added (in servers, clients, parsers, etc.)
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Support for Query resources fixed (in parser)
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Nested contained resources (e.g. encoding a resource with a contained resource that itself contains a resource)
				now parse and encode correctly, meaning that all contained resources are placed in the "contained" element
				of the root resource, and the parser looks in the root resource for all container levels when stitching
				contained resources back together.
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Server methods with @Include parameter would sometimes fail when no _include was actually
				specified in query strings.
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Client requests for IdentifierDt types (such as Patient.identifier) did not create the correct
				query string if the system is null.
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Add support for paging responses from RESTful servers.
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Don't fail on narrative blocks in JSON resources with only an XML declaration but no content (these are
				produced by the Health Intersections server) 
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Server now automatically compresses responses if the client indicates support 
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Server failed to support optional parameters when type is String and :exact qualifier is used 
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Read method in client correctly populated resource ID in returned object 
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Support added for deleted-entry by/name, by/email, and comment from Tombstones spec
			</action>
        </release>			
	</body>
</document>
