<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">

	<properties>
		<title>RESTful Client - HAPI FHIR</title>
		<author email="jamesagnew@users.sourceforge.net">James Agnew</author>
	</properties>

	<body>

		<!-- The body of the document contains a number of sections -->
		<section name="Creating a RESTful Client">

			<macro name="toc">
			</macro>

			<p>
				HAPI provides a built-in mechanism for connecting to FHIR RESTful
				servers.
				The HAPI RESTful client is designed to be easy to set up and
				to allow strong
				compile-time type checking wherever possible.
			</p>

			<p>
				There are two types of clients provided by HAPI: Generic and Annotation-driven.
				The generic client (introduced in HAPI-FHIR 0.3) is much simpler to create
				and generally provides the faster way to get started. The annotation-driven
				client can rely on code generation and static binding to specific operations to 
				give better	compile-time checking against servers with a specific set of capabilities
				exposed. 
			</p>

		</section>
		
		<section name="The Generic Client">
		
			<p>
				Creating a generic client simply requires you to create an instance of
				<code>FhirContext</code> and use that to instantiate a client.
			</p>			
			<p>
				The following example shows how to create a client, and a few operations which
				can be performed.
			</p>
			
			<macro name="snippet">
				<param name="id" value="simple" />
				<param name="file"
					value="examples/src/main/java/example/GenericClientExample.java" />
			</macro>
			
			<p> 
				<b>Performance Tip: </b> Note that FhirContext is an expensive object to create,
				so you should try to keep an instance around for the lifetime of your application. It
				is thread-safe so it can be passed as needed. Client instances, on the other hand, 
				are very inexpensive to create so you can create a new one for each request if needed 
				(although there is no requirement to do so, clients are reusable and thread-safe as well).  
			</p>

			<subsection name="Fluent Operations">
				<p>
					The generic client supports queries using a fluent interface
					which is inspired by the fantastic 
					<a href="http://ewoutkramer.github.io/fhir-net-api/client-search.html">.NET FHIR API</a>.
					The fluent interface allows you to construct powerful queries by chaining
					method calls together, leading to highly readable code. It also allows
					you to take advantage of intellisense/code completion in your favourite
					IDE.
				</p>
				<p>
					Note that most fluent operations end with an <code>execute()</code>
					statement which actually performs the invocation. You may also invoke
					several configuration operations just prior to the execute() statement,
					such as <code>encodedJson()</code> or <code>encodedXml()</code>.
				</p>
			</subsection>
						
			<subsection name="Type - Search/Query">
				
				<p>
					Searching for resources is probably the most common initial scenario for
					client applications, so we'll start the demonstration there.
				</p>
				<p>
					The following example shows how to query using the generic client:
				</p>
				<macro name="snippet">
					<param name="id" value="search" />
					<param name="file"
						value="examples/src/main/java/example/GenericClientExample.java" />
				</macro>
				
				<h4>Search - Multi-valued Parameters (ANY/OR)</h4>
				<p>
					To search for a set of possible values where <b>ANY</b> should be matched, 
					you can provide multiple values to a parameter, as shown in the example below.
					This leads to a URL resembling <code>?family=Smith,Smyth</code> 
				</p>
				<macro name="snippet">
					<param name="id" value="searchOr" />
					<param name="file"
						value="examples/src/main/java/example/GenericClientExample.java" />
				</macro>

				<h4>Search - Multi-valued Parameters (ALL/AND)</h4>
				<p>
					To search for a set of possible values where <b>ALL</b> should be matched,
					you can provide multiple instances of a marameter, as shown in the example below.
					This leads to a URL resembling <code>?address=Toronto&amp;address=Ontario&amp;address=Canada</code> 
				</p>
				<macro name="snippet">
					<param name="id" value="searchOr" />
					<param name="file"
						value="examples/src/main/java/example/GenericClientExample.java" />
				</macro>

				<h4>Search - Paging</h4>
				<p>
					If the server supports paging results, the client has a page method
					which can be used to load subsequent pages.
				</p>
				<macro name="snippet">
					<param name="id" value="searchPaging" />
					<param name="file"
						value="examples/src/main/java/example/GenericClientExample.java" />
				</macro>
				
				<h4>Search - Composite Parameters</h4>
				<p>
					If a composite parameter is being searched on, the parameter
					takes a "left" and "right" operand, each of which is
					a parameter from the resource being seached. The following example shows the
					syntax.
				</p>
				<macro name="snippet">
					<param name="id" value="searchComposite" />
					<param name="file"
						value="examples/src/main/java/example/GenericClientExample.java" />
				</macro>
				
				<h4>Search - Other Query Options</h4>
				<p>
					The fluent search also has methods for sorting, limiting, specifying
					JSON encoding, etc.
				</p>
				<macro name="snippet">
					<param name="id" value="searchAdv" />
					<param name="file"
						value="examples/src/main/java/example/GenericClientExample.java" />
				</macro>

				<h4>Search - Using HTTP POST or GET with _search</h4>
				<p>
					The FHIR specification allows several styles of search (HTTP POST, a GET with _search at the end of the URL, etc.)
					The <code>usingStyle()</code> method controls which style to use. By default, GET style is used
					unless the client detects that the request would result in a very long URL (over 8000 chars) in which
					case the client automatically switches to POST.
				</p>
				<macro name="snippet">
					<param name="id" value="searchPost" />
					<param name="file"
						value="examples/src/main/java/example/GenericClientExample.java" />
				</macro>

				<h4>Search - Compartments</h4>
				<p>
					To search a 
					<a href="http://www.hl7.org/implement/standards/fhir/extras.html#compartment">resource compartment</a>, 
					simply use the <code>withIdAndCompartment</code>
					method in your search. 
				</p>
				<macro name="snippet">
					<param name="id" value="searchCompartment" />
					<param name="file"
						value="examples/src/main/java/example/GenericClientExample.java" />
				</macro>
				
			</subsection>			

			<subsection name="Type - Create">
				<p>
					The following example shows how to perform a create
					operation using the generic client:
				</p>
				<macro name="snippet">
					<param name="id" value="create" />
					<param name="file"
						value="examples/src/main/java/example/GenericClientExample.java" />
				</macro>
			</subsection>			

			<subsection name="Instance - Read / VRead">
				<p>
					Given a resource name and ID, it is simple to retrieve
					the latest version of that resource (a 'read')
				</p>
				<macro name="snippet">
					<param name="id" value="read" />
					<param name="file"
						value="examples/src/main/java/example/GenericClientExample.java" />
				</macro>
				<p>
					By adding a version string, it is also possible to retrieve a 
					specific version (a 'vread')
				</p>
				<macro name="snippet">
					<param name="id" value="vread" />
					<param name="file"
						value="examples/src/main/java/example/GenericClientExample.java" />
				</macro>
				<p>
					It is also possible to retrieve a resource given its absolute
					URL (this will override the base URL set on the client) 
				</p>
				<macro name="snippet">
					<param name="id" value="readabsolute" />
					<param name="file"
						value="examples/src/main/java/example/GenericClientExample.java" />
				</macro>
			</subsection>			

			<subsection name="Instance - Delete">
				<p>
					The following example shows how to perform a delete
					operation using the generic client:
				</p>
				<macro name="snippet">
					<param name="id" value="delete" />
					<param name="file"
						value="examples/src/main/java/example/GenericClientExample.java" />
				</macro>
			</subsection>			

			<subsection name="Instance - Update">
				<p>
					Updating a resource is similar to creating one, except that
					an ID must be supplied since you are updating a previously
					existing resource instance.
				</p>
				<p>
					The following example shows how to perform an update
					operation using the generic client:
				</p>
				<macro name="snippet">
					<param name="id" value="update" />
					<param name="file"
						value="examples/src/main/java/example/GenericClientExample.java" />
				</macro>
			</subsection>			

			<subsection name="Server - Conformance">
				<p>
					To retrieve the server's conformance statement, simply call the <code>conformance()</code>
					method as shown below.
				</p>
				<macro name="snippet">
					<param name="id" value="conformance" />
					<param name="file"
						value="examples/src/main/java/example/GenericClientExample.java" />
				</macro>
			</subsection>			
			
			<subsection name="Server - Transaction">
				<p>
					The following example shows how to execute a transaction using the generic client:
				</p>
				<macro name="snippet">
					<param name="id" value="transaction" />
					<param name="file"
						value="examples/src/main/java/example/GenericClientExample.java" />
				</macro>
			</subsection>			
			
		</section>
		
		<section name="The Annotation-Driven Client">

			<p>
				HAPI also provides a second style of client, called the <b>annotation-driven</b> client.
			</p>

			<p>
				The design of the annotation-driven client
				is intended to be similar to that of
				JAX-WS, so users of that
				specification should be comfortable with
				this one. It uses a user-defined interface containing special
				annotated methods which HAPI binds to calls against a server.
			</p>

			<p>
				The annotation-driven client is particularly useful if you have a server that
				exposes a set of specific operations (search parameter combinations, named queries, etc.)
				and you want to let developers have a stongly/statically typed interface to that
				server.
			</p>
			<p>
				There is no difference in terms of capability between the two styles of 
				client. There is simply a difference in programming style and complexity. It
				is probably safe to say that the generic client is easier to use and leads to
				more readable code, at the expense of not giving any visibility into the 
				specific capabilities of the server you are interacting with.  
			</p>
			
			<subsection name="Defining A Restful Client Interface">

				<p>
					The first step in creating an annotation-driven client is to define a
					restful client interface.
				</p>

				<p>
					A restful client interface class must extend the
					<a href="./apidocs/ca/uhn/fhir/rest/client/api/IRestfulClient.html">IRestfulClient</a>
					interface,
					and will contain one or more methods which have been
					annotated with special annotations indicating which RESTful
					operation
					that method supports. Below is a simple example of a
					resource provider
					which supports the
					<a href="http://hl7.org/implement/standards/fhir/http.html#read">read</a>
					operation (i.e. retrieve a single resource by ID) as well as the
					<a href="http://hl7.org/implement/standards/fhir/http.html#search">search</a>
					operation (i.e. find any resources matching a given criteria) for a
					specific
					search criteria.
				</p>

				<p>
					You may notice that this interface looks a lot like the Resource
					Provider
					which is defined for use by the RESTful server. In fact, it
					supports all
					of the same annotations and is essentially identical,
					other than the
					fact that for a client you must use an interface but for a server you
					must use a concrete class with method implementations.
				</p>

				<macro name="snippet">
					<param name="id" value="provider" />
					<param name="file"
						value="examples/src/main/java/example/IRestfulClient.java" />
				</macro>

				<p>
					You will probably want to add more methods
					to your client interface.
					See
					<a href="./doc_rest_operations.html">RESTful Operations</a>
					for
					lots more examples of how to add methods for various operations.
				</p>

			</subsection>

			<subsection name="Instantiate the Client">

				<p>
					Once your client interface is created, all that is left is to
					create a FhirContext and instantiate the client and you are
					ready to
					start using it.
				</p>

				<macro name="snippet">
					<param name="id" value="client" />
					<param name="file"
						value="examples/src/main/java/example/ExampleRestfulClient.java" />
				</macro>

			</subsection>

			<subsection name="Configuring Encoding (JSON/XML)">

				<p>
					Restful client interfaces that you create will also extend
					the interface 
					<a href="./apidocs/ca/uhn/fhir/rest/client/api/IRestfulClient.html">IRestfulClient</a>,
					which comes with some helpful methods for configuring the way that
					the client will interact with the server.
				</p>
				<p>
					The following snippet shows how to configure the cliet to explicitly 
					request JSON or XML responses, and how to request "pretty printed" responses
					on servers that support this (HAPI based servers currently).				
				</p>
				
				<macro name="snippet">
					<param name="id" value="clientConfig" />
					<param name="file" value="examples/src/main/java/example/ClientExamples.java" />
				</macro>

			</subsection>
						
			<subsection name="A Complete Example">
	
				<p>
					The following is a complete example showing a RESTful client
					using
					HAPI FHIR.
				</p>
	
				<macro name="snippet">
					<param name="id" value="client" />
					<param name="file"
						value="examples/src/main/java/example/CompleteExampleClient.java" />
				</macro>
				
			</subsection>
			
		</section>

		<section name="Configuring the HTTP Client">
		
			<p>
				RESTful clients (both Generic and Annotation-Driven) use 
				<a href="http://hc.apache.org/httpcomponents-client-ga/">Apache HTTP Client</a>
				as a provider. The Apache HTTP Client is very powerful and extremely flexible, 
				but can be confusing at first to configure, because of the low-level approach that
				the library uses. 
			</p>

			<p>
				In many cases, the default configuration should suffice. However, if you require anything
				more sophisticated (username/password, HTTP proxy settings, etc.) you will need
				to configure the underlying client. 
			</p>
			
			<p>
				The underlying client configuration is provided by accessing the
				<a href="./apidocs/ca/uhn/fhir/rest/client/IRestfulClientFactory.html">IRestfulClientFactory</a>
				class from the FhirContext.
			</p>
		
			<p>
				Note that individual requests and responses
				can be tweaked using <a href="./doc_rest_client_interceptor.html">interceptors</a>.
			</p>
						
		</section>

	</body>

</document>
