<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/changes/1.0.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/changes/1.0.0 ./changes.xsd">
	<properties>
		<author>James Agnew</author>
		<title>HAPI FHIR Changelog</title>
	</properties>
	<body>
		<release version="1.2" date="2015-07-13">
			<action type="add">
				JPA server now validates QuestionnaireAnswers for conformance to their respective Questionnaire
				if one is declared.
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				SyntaxHighlightingInterceptor now also highlights OperationOutcome responses for errors/exceptions.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="126">
				Model classes do not use BoundCodeableConcept for example bindings that do not
				actually point to any codes (e.g. Observation.interpretation). Thanks
				to GitHub user @steve1medix for reporting!
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Server now exports operations as separate resources instead of as contained resources
				within Conformance
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Add new operation $get-resource-counts which will replace the resource
				count extensions exported in the Conformance statement by the JPA
				server.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="198">
				JPA server sorting often returned unexpected orders when multiple
				indexes of the same type were found on the same resource (e.g. multiple string indexed fields). Thanks to Travis Cummings for reporting!
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Add another method to IServerInterceptor which converts an exception generated on the server
				into a BaseServerResponseException. This is useful so that servers using ResponseHighlighterInterceptor
				will highlight exceptions even if they aren't created with an OperationOutcome.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="158">
				XmlParser and JsonParser in DSTU2 mode should not encode empty
				tags in resource. Thanks to Bill De Beaubien for reporting!
			</action>
			<action>
				OperationDefinitions generated by server did not properly document
				their return parameters or the type of their input parameters.
			</action>
			<action>
				Operations in server generated conformance statement should only
				appear once per name, since the name needs to be unique.
			</action>
			<action>
				Resources and datatypes are now serializable. This is an
				experimental feature which hasn't yet been extensively tested. Please test and give us your feedback!
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Switch REST server to using HttpServletRequest#getContextPath() to get
				the servlet's context path. This means that the server should behave more
				predictably, and should work in servlet 2.4 environments. Thanks to 
				Ken Zeisset for the suggestion!
			</action>
			<action type="add" issue="200">
				Vagrant environment now has an apt recipt to ensure that
				package lists are up to date. Thanks to GitHub user
				Brian S. Corbin (@corbinbs) for thr contribution!
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				JPA server and generic client now both support the _tag search parameter
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Add support for BATCH mode to JPA server transaction operation
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="192">
				Server was not correctly unescaping URL parameter values with
				a trailing comma or an escaped backslash. Thanks to GitHub user
				@SherryH for all of her help in diagnosing this issue!
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Avoid crash when parsing if an invalid child element is found in 
				a resource reference.
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Create new android specialty libraries for DSTU1 and DSTU2
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Throwing a server exception (e.g. AuthenticationException) in a server interceptor's 
				incomingRequestPreProcessed method resulted in the server returning an HTTP 500 instead
				of the appropriate error code for the exception being thrown. Thanks to Nagesh Bashyam 
				for reporting!
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="207">
				Fix issue in JSON parser where invalid contained resources (missing
				a resourceType element) fail to parse with a confusing NullPointerException.
				Thanks to GitHub user @hugosoares for reporting!
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				JPA server now implements the $validate-code operation
			</action>
			<action type="add" fix="125">
				HAPI-FHIR now has support for _summary and _elements parameters, in server, client,
				and JPA server.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" fix="209">
				_revinclude results from JPA server should have a Bundle.entry.search.mode of
				"include" and not "match". Thanks to Josh Mandel for reporting!
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Resource references using resource instance objects instead of resource IDs 
				will correctly qualify the IDs with the resource type if they aren't already qualified   
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="1.1" date="2015-07-13">
			<action type="add">
				Add support for reference implementation structures.
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Parsers did not encode the resource meta element if the resource 
				had tags but no other meta elements. Thanks to Bill de Beaubien and
				Claude Nanjo for finding this.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="164">
				Correct performance issue with :missing=true search requests where the parameter is a resource link. Thanks to wanghaisheng for all his help in testing this.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="149">
				The self link in the Bundle returned by searches on the server does not respect the
				server's address strategy (which resulted in an internal IP being shown on fhirtest.uhn.ca)
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Introduce ResponseHighlighterInterceptor, which provides syntax highlighting on RESTful server responses
				if the server detects that the request is coming from a browser. This interceptor has been added
				to fhirtest.uhn.ca responses.
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Performing a create operation in a client used an incorrect URL if the
				resource had an ID set. ID should be ignored for creates. Thanks to 
				Peter Girard for reporting!
			</action>
			<action type="add" issue="170">
				Add better addXXX() methods to structures, which take the datatype being added as a parameter. Thanks to Claude Nanjo for the
				suggestion!
			</action>
			<action type="add" issue="152">
				Add a new parser validation mechanism (see the 
				<![CDATA[<a href="./doc_validation.html">validation page</a>]]> for info) which can be 
				used to validate resources as they are being parsed, and optionally fail if invalid/unexpected
				elements are found in resource bodies during parsing. 
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				IParser#parseResource(Class, String) method, which is used to parse a resource into the given
				structure will now throw a DataFormatException if the structure is for the wrong type of
				resource for the one actually found in the input String (or Reader). For example, if a Patient
				resource is being parsed into Organization.class this will now cause an error. Previously,
				the XML parser would ignore the type and the JSON parser would fail. This also caused 
				operations to not parse correctly if they returned a resource type other than
				parameters with JSON encoding (e.g. the $everything operation on UHN's test server).
				Thanks to Avinash Shanbhag for reporting!
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Web tester UI now supports _revinclude
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="178">
				Support link elements in Bundle.entry when parsing in DSTU2 mode
				using the old (non-resource) Bundle class. Thanks to GitHub user
				@joedai for reporting!
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				LoggingInterceptor for server now supports logging DSTU2 extended operations by name
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Woodstox XML parser has a default setting to limit the maximum
				length of an attribute to 512kb. This caused issues handling
				large attachments, so this setting has been increased to 100Mb.
				Thanks to Nikos Kyriakoulakos for reporting!
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="175">
				Some HTML entities were not correctly converted during parsing. Thanks to
				Nick Kitto for reporting!
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				In the JPA Server:
				Transactions creating resources with temporary/placeholder resource IDs
				and other resources with references to those placeholder IDs previously
				did not work if the reference did not contain the resource type
				(e.g. Patient/urn:oid:0.1.2.3 instead of urn:oid:0.1.2.3). The
				latter is actually the correct way of specifying a reference to a
				placeholder, but the former was the only way that worked. Both forms
				now work, in order to be lenient. Thanks to Bill De Beaubien for
				reporting!
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				When parsing Bundles, if Bundle.entry.base is set to "cid:" (for DSTU1) 
				or "urn:uuid:" / "urn:oid:" (for DSTU2) this is now correctly passed as
				the base in resource.getId(). Conversely, when
				encoding bundles, if a resource ID has a base defined,
				and Bundle.entry.base is empty, it will now be
				automatically set by the parser.
			</action>
			<action type="add" issue="179">
				Add fluent client method for validate operation, and support the
				new DSTU2 style extended operation for $validate if the client is
				in DSTU2 mode. Thanks to Eric from the FHIR Skype Implementers chat for
				reporting.
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Server now supports complete Accept header content negotiation, including
				q values specifying order of preference. Previously the q value was ignored.
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Server in DSTU2 mode now indicates that whether it has support for Transaction operation or not. Thanks to Kevin Paschke for pointing out that this wasn't working!
			</action>
			<action type="add" issue="166">
				Questionnaire.title now gets correctly indexed in JPA server (it has no path, so it is a special case)
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				JPA server now supports ifNoneMatch in GET within a transaction request.
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				DateRangeParam now supports null values in the constructor for lower or upper bounds (but 
				still not both)
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Generic/fluent client and JPA server now both support _lastUpdated search parameter
				which was added in DSTU2
			</action>
			<action name="fix" issue="188">
				JPA server now supports sorting on reference parameters. Thanks to
				Vishal Kachroo for reporting that this wasn't working!
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Prevent Last-Updated header in responses coming back to the client from
				overwriting the 'lastUpdated' value in the meta element in DSTU2
				resources. This is important because 'lastUpdated' can have more
				precision than the equivalent header, but the client previously
				gave the header priority.
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				JPA server supports _count parameter in transaction containing search URL (nested search)
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				DSTU2 servers now indicate support for conditional create/update/delete in their
				conformance statement.
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Support for the Prefer header has been added to the server, client, and
				JPA modules.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="196">
				JPA server failed to search for deep chained parameters across multiple references,
				e.g. "Location.partof.partof.organization". Thanks to Ismael Sarmento Jr for
				reporting!
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Prevent crash when encoding resources with contained resources 
				if the contained resources contained a circular reference to each other
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Add $meta, $meta-add, and $meta-delete operations to generic client
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="1.0" date="2015-04-08">
			<action type="add">
				Bump the version of a few dependencies to the
				latest versions:
				<![CDATA[
					<ul>
						<li>Phloc-commons (for schematron validation) 4.3.5 -> 4.3.6</li>
						<li>Apache HttpClient 4.3.6 -> 4.4</li>
						<li>Woodstox 4.4.0 -> 4.4.1</li>
						<li>SLF4j 1.7.9 -> 1.7.10</li>
						<li>Spring (used in hapi-fhir-jpaserver-base module) 4.1.3.RELEASE -> 4.1.5.RELEASE</li>
					</ul>
				]]>
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Add support for "profile" and "tag" elements in the resource Meta block
				when parsing DSTU2 structures.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="113">
				When a user manually creates the list of contained resources in a resource,
				the encoder fails to encode any resources that don't have a '#' at the
				start of their ID. This is unintuitive, so we now assume that '123' means '#123'.
				Thanks to myungchoi for reporting and providing a test case!
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Add methods for setting the default encoding (XML/JSON) and
				oretty print behaviour in the Fluent Client. Thanks to Stackoverflow
				user ewall for the idea.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="129">
				JPA Server did not mark a resource as "no longer deleted" if it
				was updated after being deleted. Thanks to Elliott Lavy and Lloyd
				McKenzie for reporting!
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="128">
				Fix regression in 0.9 - Server responds with an HTTP 500 and a NullPointerException instead of an HTTP 400 and a useful error message if the client requests an unknown resource type
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Add support for 
				<![CDATA[<code>_revinclude</code>]]>
				parameter in client, server, and JPA.
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Include constants on resources (such as 
				<![CDATA[<code>Observation.INCLUDE_VALUE_STRING</code>]]>)
				have been switched in the DSTU2 structures to use
				the new syntax required in DSTU2: [resource name]:[search param NAME]
				insead of the DSTU1 style [resource name].[search param PATH]
			</action>
			<action type="add" fix="124">
				When encoding resources, the parser will now convert any resource
				references to versionless references automatically (i.e. it will 
				omit the version part automatically if one is present in the reference)
				since references between resources must be versionless. Additionally,
				references in server responses will omit the server base URL part of the
				reference if the base matches the base for the server giving
				the response.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" fix="130">
				Narrative generator incorrectly sets the Resource.text.status to 'generated' even if the
				given resource type does not have a template (and therefore no narrative is actually generated).
				Thanks to Bill de Beaubien for reporting!
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Searching in JPA server with no search parameter returns deleted resources when it should exclude them.
			</action>
			<action type="add" fix="135">
				Remove Eclipse and IntelliJ artifacts (.project, *.iml, etc) from version control. Thanks
				to Doug Martin for the suggestion!
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				REST server methods may now have a parameter of
				type NarrativeModeEnum which will be populated with
				the value of the _narrative URL parameter
				if one was supplied. Annotation client methods 
				may also include a parameter of this type, and it
				will be used to populate this parameter on the request
				URL if it is not null. Thanks to Neal Acharya for the
				idea!
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Android JAR now includes servlet-API classes, as the project will not
				work without them. Thanks 
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="116">
				Requested _include values are preserved across paging links when the
				server returns multiple pages. Thanks to Bill de Beaubien for 
				reporting! 
			</action>
			<action type="add" issue="138" dev="wdebeau1">
				Add new server address strategy "ApacheProxyAddressStrategy" which uses 
				headers "x-forwarded-host" and "x-forwarded-proto" to determine the
				server's address. This is useful if you are deploying a HAPI FHIR 
				server behind an Apache proxy (e.g. for load balancing or other reasons).
				Thanks to Bill de Beaubien for contributing!
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="143">
				Resource references between separate resources found in a single
				bundle did not get populated with the actual resource when parsing a
				DSTU2 style bundle. Thanks to Nick Peterson for reporting and figuring
				out why none of our unit tests were actually catching the problem!
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="146">
				JSON encoder did not encode contained resources when encoding
				a DSTU2 style bundle. Thanks to Mohammad Jafari and baopingle
				for all of their help in tracking this issue down and developing
				useful unit tests to demonstrate it.
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Client now supports invoking transcation using a DSTU2-style
				Bundle resource as the input.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="147">
				JPA Server $everything operation could sometimes include a duplicate copy of 
				the main focus resource if it was referred to in a deep chain. Thanks
				to David Hay for reporting!
			</action>
			<action type="add" issue="148">
				JPA Server $everything operation now allows a _count parameter
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="139">
				JPA server failed to index resources containing ContactPointDt elements with
				populated values (e.g. Patient.telecom). Thanks to Mohammad Jafari for reporting!
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Add a new configuration method on the parsers, 
				<![CDATA[<code>setStripVersionsFromReferences(boolean)</code>]]> which
				configures the parser to preserve versions in resource reference links when
				encoding. By default, these are removed.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="155" dev="wdebeau1">
				Terser's IModelVisitor now supplies to the path to the element. This is
				an API change, but I don't think there are many users of the IModelVisitor yet.
				Please let us know if this is a big hardship and we can find an alternate way
				of making this change.
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Prevent server from returning a Content-Location header for search
				response when using the DSTU2 bundle format
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				JPA server (uhnfhirtest.uhn.ca) sometimes included an empty
				"text" element in Bundles being returned.
			</action>
			<action type="add" issue="162">
				Add a framework for the Web Tester UI to allow its internal FHIR client to 
				be configured (e.g. to add an authorization interceptor so that it adds
				credentials to client requests it makes). Thanks to Harsha Kumara for
				the suggestion!
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="163">
				Fix regression in early 1.0 builds where resource type sometimes does not get 
				populated in a resource ID when the resource is parsed. Thanks to
				Nick Peterson for reporting, and for providing a test case!
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Allow fluent/generic client users to execute a transaction using a raw string (containing a bundle resource)
				as input instead of a Bundle resource class instance.
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Disable date validation in the web tester UI, so that it is possible to 
				enter partial dates, or dates without times, or even test out invalid date
				options.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="36">
				Make BaseElement#getUndeclaredExtensions() and BaseElement#getUndeclaredExtensions() return
				a mutable list so that it is possible to delete extensions from a resource instance.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="168">
				Server conformance statement check in clients (this is the check
				where the first time a given FhirContext is used to access a given server
				base URL, it will first check the server's Conformance statement to ensure
				that it supports the correct version of FHIR) now uses any 
				registered client interceptors. In addition, IGenericClient now has a method
				"forceConformanceCheck()" which manually triggers this check. Thanks to
				Doug Martin for reporting and suggesting!
			</action>
			<action type="add" issue="167">
				Rename the Spring Bean definition for the JPA server EntityManager from
				"myEntityManagerFactory" to just "entityManagerFactory" as this is the
				default bean name expected in other parts of the Spring framework. 
				Thanks to Mohammad Jafari for the suggestion!
			</action>
			<action type="add" issue="164">
				Improve error message when a user tries to perform a create/update with an invalid
				or missing Content-Type header. Thanks to wanghaisheng for reporting! (This was
				actually a three part bug, so the following two fixes also reference this
				bug number)
			</action>
			<action type="add" issue="164">
				Add support for :missing qualifier in generic/fluent client.
			</action>
			<action type="add" issue="164">
				Add support for :missing qualifier in JPA server.
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Add a new configuration method on the parsers, 
				<![CDATA[<code>setStripVersionsFromReferences(boolean)</code>]]> which
				configures the parser to preserve versions in resource reference links when
				encoding. By default, these are removed.
			</action>
			<action type="add" due-to="joel-costigliola" issue="171">
				Add an exception for RESTful clients/servers to represent the
				HTTP 403 Forbidden status code. Thanks to Joel Costigliola for
				the patch!
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Transaction server operations incorrectly used the "Accept" header instead of the "Content-Type" header to determine the
				POST request encoding. Thanks to Rene Spronk for providing a test case!
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="0.9" date="2015-03-14">
			<action type="add">
				Support for DSTU2 features introduced: New resource definitions, Bundle resource, 
				encoding changes (ID in resource bodt, meta tag)
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="65">
				Fix an issue encoding extensions on primitive types in JSON. Previously the "_value" object
				would be an array even if the field it was extending was not repeatable. This is not correct
				according to the specification, nor can HAPI's parser parse this correctly. The encoder
				has been corrected, and the parser has been adjusted to be able to handle resources with
				extensions encoded in this way. Thanks to Mohammad Jafari for reporting!
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Library now checks if custom resource types can be instantiated on startup
				(e.g. because they don't have a no-argument constructor) in order to 
				avoid failing later
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Bump a few dependency JARs to the latest versions in Maven POM:
				<![CDATA[
					<ul>
						<li>SLF4j (in base module) - Bumped to 1.7.9</li>
						<li>Apache HTTPClient (in base module) - Bumped to 4.3.6</li>
						<li>Hibernate (in JPA module) - Bumped to 4.3.7</li>
					</ul>
				]]>
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="67">
				IdDt failed to recognize local identifiers containing fragments that look like 
				real identifiers as being local identifiers even though they started with '#'.
				For example, a local resource reference of "#aa/_history/aa" would be incorrectly
				parsed as a non-local reference.
				Thanks to Mohammad Jafari for reporting!
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				<![CDATA[<code>Last-Modified</code>]]>
				header in server was incorrectly using FHIR date format instead
				of RFC-1123 format. 
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Server create and update methods failed with an IllegalArgumentException if
				the method type was a custom resource definition type (instead of a built-in
				HAPI type). Thanks to Neal Acharya for the analysis. 
			</action>
			<action type="add" fix="79">
				JPA server module now supports 
				<![CDATA[<code>_include</code>]]> 
				value of 
				<![CDATA[<code>*</code>]]>. Thanks to Bill de Beaubien for reporting! 
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				IdDt method 
				<![CDATA[withServerBase]]>
				returned String (unlike all of the other "withFoo" methods on that class),
				and did not work correctly if the IdDt already had a server base. This
				has been corrected. Note that the return type for this method has been
				changed, so code may need to be updated.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="84" due-to="mochaholic">
				In previous versions of HAPI, the XML parser encoded multiple contained
				resources in a single 
				<![CDATA[<code>&lt;contained&gt;&lt;/contained&gt;</code>]]>
				tag, even though the FHIR specification rerquires a separate
				<![CDATA[<code>&lt;contained&gt;&lt;/contained&gt;</code>]]>
				tag for each resource. This has been corrected. Note that the parser will
				correctly parse either form (this has always been the case) so this
				change should not cause any breakage in HAPI based trading partners, but
				may cause issues if other applications have been coded to depend on the
				incorrect behaviour. Thanks to Mochaholic for reporting! 
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="91" due-to="andyhuang91">
				Custom/user defined resource definitions which contained more than one
				child with no order defined failed to initialize properly. Thanks to
				Andy Huang for reporting and figuring out where the
				problem was! 
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				RESTful Client now queries the server (only once per server base URL) to ensure that
				the given server corresponds to the correct version of the FHIR specification, as
				defined by the FhirContext. This behaviour can be disabled by setting the
				appropriate configuration on the 
				RestfulClientConfig. Thanks to Grahame Grieve for the suggestion!
			</action>
			<action type="add">
			    JPA module now supports deleting resource via transaction
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="97" due-to="twilson650">
				DateClientParam#second() incorrectly used DAY precision instead
				of SECOND precision. Thanks to Tom Wilson for the pull request!
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="100" due-to="sweetnavelorange">
				Fix issue where HAPI failed to initialize correctly if Woodstox library was not on the classpath, even
				if StAX API was configured to use a different provider. Thanks to
				James Butler for reporting and figuring out where the issue was!
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="101">
				Calling BaseDateTimeDt#setValue(Date, TemporalPrecisionEnum) did not always actually respect
				the given precision when the value was encoded. Thanks to jacksonjesse for
				reporting!
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="103">
				Encoders (both XML and JSON) will no longer encode contained resources if they are 
				not referenced anywhere in the resource via a local reference. This is just a convenience
				for users who have parsed a resource with contained resources and want to remove some
				before re-encoding. Thanks to Alexander Kley for reporting! 
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="110" due-to="mochaholic">
				Add support for DSTU2 style security labels in the parser and encoder. Thanks to
				Mohammad Jafari for the contribution!
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Server requests for Binary resources where the client has explicitly requested XML or JSON responses
				(either with a <![CDATA[<code>_format</code>]]> URL parameter, or an <![CDATA[<code>Accept</code>]]> request header)
				will be responded to using the Binary FHIR resource type instead of as Binary blobs. This is
				in accordance with the recommended behaviour in the FHIR specification.
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Add new properties to RestfulServer: "DefaultResponseEncoding", which allows
				users to configure a default encoding (XML/JSON) to use if none is specified in the
				client request. Currently defaults to XML. Also "DefaultPrettyPrint", which specifies
				whether to pretty print responses by default. Both properties can be overridden
				on individual requets using the appropriate Accept header or request URL parameters.
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Add support for quantity search params in FHIR tester UI
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Add support for FHIR "extended operations" as defined in the FHIR DSTU2
				specification, for the Generic Client, Annotation Client, and
				Server.  
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Observation.applies[x] and other similar search fields with multiple allowable 
				value types were not being correctly indexed in the JPA server.    
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="122">
				DateClientParam.before() incorrectly placed "&lt;=" instead of 
				"&lt;" in the request URL. Thanks to Ryan for reporting!    
			</action>
			<action type="add" issue="77" dev="wdebeau1">
				Server now only automatically adds _include resources which are provided
				as references if the client request actually requested that specific include.
				See RestfulServer
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="120">
				User defined resource types which contain extensions that use a bound code type
				(e.g. an BoundCodeDt with a custom Enum) failed to parse correctly. Thanks
				to baopingle for reporting and providing a test case!
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Sorting is now supported in the Web Testing UI (previously a button existed for sorting, but it didn't do anything)
			</action>
			<action type="add" issue="111">
				Server will no longer include stack traces in the OperationOutcome returned to the client
				when an exception is thrown. A new interceptor called ExceptionHandlingInterceptor has been
				created which adds this functionality back if it is needed (e.g. for DEV setups). See the 
				server interceptor documentation for more information. Thanks to Andy Huang for the suggestion!
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="0.8" date="2014-12-17">
			<action type="add">
				<![CDATA[<b>API CHANGE:</b>]]> The "FHIR structures" for DSTU1 (the classes which model the
				resources and composite datatypes) have been moved out of the core JAR into their
				own JAR, in order to allow support for DEV resources, and DSTU2 resources when thast
				version is finalized. See the
				<![CDATA[<a href="./doc_dstu2.html">DSTU2 page</a>]]> 
				for more information.  
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				<![CDATA[
					<b>Deprocated API Removal</b>: The following classes (which were deprocated previously)
					have now been removed:
					<ul>
						<li><b>ISecurityManager</b>: If you are using this class, the same functionality
						is available through the more general purpose
						<a href="http://jamesagnew.github.io/hapi-fhir/doc_rest_server_interceptor.html">server interceptor</a>
						capabilities.
						<li><b>CodingListParam</b>: This class was made redundant by the
						<a href="http://jamesagnew.github.io/hapi-fhir/apidocs/ca/uhn/fhir/rest/param/TokenOrListParam.html">TokenOrListParam</a>
						class, which can be used in its place.
					</ul>
				]]> 
			</action>			
			<action type="add">
				<![CDATA[
					<b>API Change</b>: The IResource#getResourceMetadata() method has been changed
					from returning 
					<code>Map&lt;ResourceMetadataKeyEnum&lt;?&gt;, Object&gt;</code>
					to returning a new type called
					<code>ResourceMetadataMap</code>. This new type implements 
					<code>Map&lt;ResourceMetadataKeyEnum&lt;?&gt;, Object&gt;</code>
					itself, so this change should not break existing code, but may
					require a clean build in order to run correctly.
				]]> 
			</action>			
			<action type="add" issue="38" dev="wdebeau1">
				Profile generation on the server was not working due to IdDt being
				incorrectly used. Thanks to Bill de Beaubien for the pull request!
			</action>			
			<action type="add" issue="42" dev="wdebeau1">
				Profiles did not generate correctly if a resource definition class had a 
				defined extension which was of a composite type. Thanks to Bill de Beaubien for the pull request!
			</action>			
			<action type="add" issue="44" dev="petromykhailysyn">
				Remove unnecessary IOException from narrative generator API. Thanks to
				Petro Mykhailysyn for the pull request!  
			</action>			
			<action type="add" issue="48" dev="wdebeau1">
				Introduced a new 
				<![CDATA[<code>@ProvidesResources</code>]]> annotation which can be added to
				resource provider and servers to allow them to declare additional resource
				classes they are able to serve. This is useful if you have a server which can
				serve up multiple classes for the same resource type (e.g. a server that sometimes
				returns a default Patient, but sometimes uses a custom subclass). 
				Thanks to Bill de Beaubien for the pull request!
			</action>
			<action type="add" issue="49" dev="wdebeau1">
				Introduced a new 
				<![CDATA[<code>@Destroy</code>]]> annotation which can be added to
				a resource provider method. This method will be called by the server when it
				is being closed/destroyed (e.g. when the application is being undeployed, the
				container is being shut down, etc.) 
				Thanks to Bill de Beaubien for the pull request!
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Add a new method <![CDATA[handleException]]> to the server interceptor
				framework which allows interceptors to be notified of any exceptions and 
				runtime errors within server methods. Interceptors may optionally also
				override the default error handling behaviour of the RestfulServer.
			</action>
			<action dev="wdebeau1" type="add">
				Add constants to BaseResource for the "_id" search parameter which all resources
				should support.
			</action>			
			<action type="fix">
				DateRangeParam parameters on the server now return correct 
				<![CDATA[<code>getLowerBoundAsInstant()</code>]]>
				and 
				<![CDATA[<code>getUpperBoundAsInstant()</code>]]>
				values if a single unqualified value is passed in. For example, if
				a query containing 
				<![CDATA[<code>&birthdate=2012-10-01</code>]]> 
				is received, previously these two methods would both return the same
				value, but with this fix 
				<![CDATA[<code>getUpperBoundAsInstant()</code>]]>
				now returns the instant at 23:59:59.9999.				
			</action>			
			<action type="fix">
				Resource fields with a type of "*" (or Any) sometimes failed to parse if a 
				value type of "code" was used. Thanks to Bill de Beaubien for reporting!
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="lmds">
				Remove dependency on JAXB libraries, which were used to parse and encode
				dates and times (even in the JSON parser). JAXB is built in to most JDKs
				but the version bundled with IBM's JDK is flaky and resulted in a number
				of problems when deploying to Websphere.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="50" dev="jjathman">
				Primitive datatypes now preserve their original string value when parsing resources,
				as well as containing the "parsed value". For instance, a DecimalDt field value of
				<![CDATA[<code>1.0000</code>]]> will be parsed into the corresponding 
				decimal value, but will also retain the original value with the corresponding
				level of precision. This allows vadliator rules to be applied to 
				original values as received "over the wire", such as well formatted but
				invalid dates, e.g. "2001-15-01". Thanks to Joe Athman for reporting and 
				helping to come up with a fix!
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				When using Generic Client, if performing a
				<![CDATA[create]]> or <![CDATA[update]]> operation using a String as the resource body,
				the client will auto-detect the FHIR encoding style and send an appropriate 
				<![CDATA[Content-Type]]> header.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="52">
				JPA module (and public HAPI-FHIR test server) were unable to process resource types
				where at least one search parameter has no path specified. These now correctly save
				(although the server does not yet process these params, and it should). Thanks to
				GitHub user shvoidlee for reporting and help with analysis!
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Generic/Fluent Client "create" and "update" method requests were not setting a content type header
			</action>
			<action type="add" issue="53" dev="petromykhailysyn">
				DateDt left precision value as <![CDATA[null]]> in the constructor
				<![CDATA[DateDt(Date)]]>.
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				RESTful server now doesn't overwrite resource IDs if they are absolute. In other words, if
				a server's Resource Provider returns a resource with ID "Patient/123" it will be translated to
				"[base url]/Patient/123" but if the RP returns ID "http://foo/Patient/123" the ID will be
				returned exactly as is. Thanks to Bill de Beaubien for the suggestion!
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="55">
				JPA module Transaction operation was not correctly replacing logical IDs
				beginning with "cid:" with server assigned IDs, as required by the
				specification.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="tahurac">
				<![CDATA[FhirTerser]]> did not visit or find children in contained resources when 
				searching a resource. This caused server implementations to not always return contained
				resources when they are included with a resource being returned.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="lmds">
				Add a method <![CDATA[String IResource#getResourceName()]]> which returns the name of the
				resource in question (e.g. "Patient", or "Observation"). This is intended as a 
				convenience to users. 
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Do not strip version from resource references in resources returned
				from server search methods. Thanks to Bill de Beaubien for reporting!
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="jjathman" issue="54">
				Correct an issue with the validator where changes to the underlying
				OperationOutcome produced by a validation cycle cause the validation
				results to be incorrect.
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Client interceptors registered to an interface based client instance 
				were applied to other client instances for the same client interface as well. (Issue
				did not affect generic/fluent clients)
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="57">
				DateDt, DateTimeDt and types InstantDt types now do not throw an exception
				if they are used to parse a value with the wrong level of precision for
				the given type but do throw an exception if the wrong level of precision
				is passed into their constructors.<![CDATA[<br/><br/>]]>
				This means that HAPI FHIR can now successfully parse resources from external 
				sources that have the wrong level of precision, but will generate a validation
				error if the resource is validated. Thanks to Alexander Kley for the suggestion!
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Encoding a Binary resource without a content type set should not result in a NullPointerException. Thanks
				to Alexander Kley for reporting!
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Server gives a more helpful error message if multiple IResourceProvider implementations
				are provided for the same resource type. Thanks to wanghaisheng for the idea!
			</action>
			<action type="add" issue="61">
				Bring DSTU1 resource definitions up to version 0.0.82-2929<![CDATA[<br/>]]>
				Bring DEV resource definitions up to 0.4.0-3775<![CDATA[<br/>]]>
				Thanks to crinacimpian for reporting!
			</action>
			<action type="add" issue="62">
				JPA server did not correctly process _include requests if included 
				resources were present with a non-numeric identifier. Thanks to 
				Bill de Beaubien for reporting!
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="60">
				Client requests which include a resource/bundle body (e.g. create,
				update, transaction) were not including a charset in the content type
				header, leading to servers incorrectly assuming ISO-8859/1. Thanks to 
				shvoidlee for reporting!
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="59" dev="wdebeau1">
				Clean up the way that Profile resources are automatically exported
				by the server for custom resource profile classes. See the 
				<![CDATA[<a href="http://jamesagnew.github.io/hapi-fhir/apidocs/ca/uhn/fhir/model/api/annotation/ResourceDef.html">@ResourceDef</a>]]>
				JavaDoc for information on how this works.
			</action>
			<action type="add" issue="73" dev="wdebeau1">
				Add convenience methods to TokenOrListParam to test whether any of a set of tokens match
				the given requested list.
			</action>
			<action type="add" issue="86" dev="harsha89">
				Add a protected method to RestfulServer which allows developers to 
				implement their own method for determining which part of the request
				URL is the FHIR request path (useful if you are embedding the RestulServer inside
				of another web framework). Thanks to Harsha Kumara for the pull request!
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="0.7" date="2014-10-23">
			<action type="add" issue="30">
				<![CDATA[<b>API CHANGE:</b>]]> The TagList class previously implemented ArrayList semantics,
				but this has been replaced with LinkedHashMap semantics. This means that the list of
				tags will no longer accept duplicate tags, but that tag order will still be
				preserved. Thanks to Bill de Beaubien for reporting!
			</action>			
			<action type="fix" issue="33">
				Server was incorrectly including contained resources being returned as both contained resources, and as 
				top-level resources in the returned bundle for search operations.
				Thanks to Bill de Beaubien for reporting! This also fixes Issue #20, thanks to
				lephty for reporting!
			</action>			
			<action type="add" dev="suranga">
				Documentation fixes
			</action>			
			<action type="add" dev="dougmartin">
				Add a collection of new methods on the generic client which support the
				<![CDATA[ 
				<b><a href="./apidocs/ca/uhn/fhir/rest/client/IGenericClient.html#read(java.lang.Class,%20ca.uhn.fhir.model.primitive.UriDt)">read</a></b>,
				<b><a href="./apidocs/ca/uhn/fhir/rest/client/IGenericClient.html#vread(java.lang.Class,%20ca.uhn.fhir.model.primitive.UriDt)">read</a></b>,
				and <b><a href="./apidocs/ca/uhn/fhir/rest/client/IGenericClient.html#search(java.lang.Class,%20ca.uhn.fhir.model.primitive.UriDt)">search</a></b>
				]]>
				operations using an absolute URL. This allows developers to perform these operations using
				URLs they obtained from other sources (or external resource references within resources). In
				addition, the existing read/vread operations will now access absolute URL references if
				they are passed in. Thanks to Doug Martin of the Regenstrief Center for Biomedical Informatics
				for contributing this implementation!
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Server implementation was not correctly figuring out its own FHIR Base URL when deployed
				on Amazon Web Service server. Thanks to Jeffrey Ting and Bill De Beaubien of
				Systems Made Simple for their help in figuring out this issue! 
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				XML Parser failed to encode fields with both a resource reference child and
				a primitive type child. Thanks to Jeffrey Ting and Bill De Beaubien of
				Systems Made Simple for their help in figuring out this issue!
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				HAPI now runs successfully on Servlet 2.5 containers (such as Tomcat 6). Thanks to
				Bernard Gitaadji for reporting and diagnosing the issue!
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Summary (in the bundle entry) is now encoded by the XML and JSON parsers if supplied. Thanks to David Hay of 
				Orion Health for reporting this!
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="24">
				Conformance profiles which are automatically generated by the server were missing a few mandatory elements,
				which meant that the profile did not correctly validate. Thanks to Bill de Beaubien of Systems Made Simple
				for reporting this!				
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				XHTML (in narratives) containing escapable characters (e.g. &lt; or &quot;) will now always have those characters 
				escaped properly in encoded messages.
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Resources containing entities which are not valid in basic XML (e.g. &amp;sect;) will have those
				entities converted to their equivalent unicode characters when resources are encoded, since FHIR does
				not allow extended entities in resource instances.
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Add a new client interceptor which adds HTTP Authorization Bearer Tokens (for use with OAUTH2 servers)
				to client requests.
			</action>			
			<action type="fix">
				Add phloc-commons dependency explicitly, which resolves an issue building HAPI from source on
				some platforms. Thanks to Odysseas Pentakalos for the patch!
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				HAPI now logs a single line indicating the StAX implementation being used upon the
				first time an XML parser is created.
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Update methods on the server did not return a "content-location" header, but
				only a "location" header. Both are required according to the FHIR specification.
				Thanks to Bill de Beaubien of Systems Made Simple for reporting this!				
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="26" dev="akley">
				Parser failed to correctly read contained Binary resources. Thanks to Alexander Kley for
				the patch! 
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="29" dev="akley">
				Calling encode multiple times on a resource with contained resources caused the contained
				resources to be re-added (and the actual message to grow) with each encode pass. Thanks to
				Alexander Kley for the test case!
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				JSON-encoded contained resources with the incorrect "_id" element (which should be "id", but some
				incorrect examples exist on the FHIR specification) now parse correctly. In other words, HAPI 
				previously only accepted the correct "id" element, but now it also accepts the incorrect
				"_id" element just to be more lenient.				
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Several unit tests failed on Windows (or any platform with non UTF-8 default encoding). This may
				have also caused resource validation to fail occasionally on these platforms as well.
				Thanks to Bill de Beaubien for reporting!
			</action>			
			<action type="fix">
				toString() method on TokenParam was incorrectly showing the system as the value.
				Thanks to Bill de Beaubien for reporting!
			</action>			
			<action type="update">
				Documentation on contained resources contained a typo and did not actually produce contained resources. Thanks
				to David Hay of Orion Health for reporting!
			</action>			
			<action type="add" issue="31" dev="preston">
				Add a 
				<![CDATA[<a href="https://www.vagrantup.com/">Vagrant</a>]]>  
				based environment (basically a fully built, self contained development environment) for
				trying out the HAPI server modules. Thanks to Preston Lee for the pull request, and for 
				offering to maintain this! 
			</action>
			<action type="add" issue="32" dev="jjathman">
				Change validation API so that it uses a return type instead of exceptions to communicate 
				validation failures. Thanks to Joe Athman for the pull request!
			</action>
			<action type="add" issue="35" dev="petromykhailysyn">
				Add a client interceptor which adds an HTTP cookie to each client request. Thanks to 
				Petro Mykhailysyn for the pull request! 
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="0.6" date="2014-09-08" description="This release brings a number of new features and bug fixes!">
			<!-- 
			<action type="add">
				Allow generic client  ... OAUTH
			</action>
			-->
			<action type="add">
				Add server interceptor framework, and new interceptor for logging incoming
				requests.   
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Add server validation framework for validating resources against the FHIR schemas and schematrons
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Tester UI created double _format and _pretty param entries in searches. Thanks to Gered King of University
				Health Network for reporting!   
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="4">
				Create method was incorrectly returning an HTTP 204 on sucessful completion, but
				should be returning an HTTP 200 per the FHIR specification. Thanks to wanghaisheng 
				for reporting! 
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				FHIR Tester UI now correctly sends UTF-8 charset in responses so that message payloads containing
				non US-ASCII characters will correctly display in the browser
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				JSON parser was incorrectly encoding extensions on composite elements outside the element itself
				(as is done correctly for non-composite elements) instead of inside of them. Thanks to David Hay of
				Orion for reporting this!
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Contained/included resource instances received by a client are now automatically 
				added to any ResourceReferenceDt instancea in other resources which reference them.
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Add documentation on how to use eBay CORS Filter to support Cross Origin Resource
				Sharing (CORS) to server. CORS support that was built in to the server itself has
				been removed, as it did not work correctly (and was reinventing a wheel that others
				have done a great job inventing). Thanks to Peter Bernhardt of Relay Health for all the assistance
				in testing this!
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				IResource interface did not expose the getLanguage/setLanguage methods from BaseResource,
				so the resource language was difficult to access.
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				JSON Parser now gives a more friendly error message if it tries to parse JSON with invalid use 
				of single quotes
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Transaction server method is now allowed to return an OperationOutcome in addition to the
				incoming resources. The public test server now does this in order to return status information
				about the transaction processing.
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Update method in the server can now flag (via a field on the MethodOutcome object being returned)
				that the result was actually a creation, and Create method can indicate that it was actually an
				update. This has no effect other than to switch between the HTTP 200 and HTTP 201 status codes on the
				response, but this may be useful in some circumstances.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="tahurac">
				Annotation client search methods with a specific resource type (e.g. List&lt;Patient&gt; search())
				won't return any resources that aren't of the correct type that are received in a response
				bundle (generally these are referenced resources, so they are populated in the reference fields instead).
				Thanks to Tahura Chaudhry of University Health Network for the unit test!
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Added narrative generator template for OperationOutcome resource
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Date/time types did not correctly parse values in the format "yyyymmdd" (although the FHIR-defined format
				is "yyyy-mm-dd" anyhow, and this is correctly handled). Thanks to Jeffrey Ting of Systems Made Simple
				for reporting! 
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Server search method for an unnamed query gets called if the client requests a named query
				with the same parameter list. Thanks to Neal Acharya of University Health Network for reporting!			
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Category header (for tags) is correctly read in client for "read" operation
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Transaction method in server can now have parameter type Bundle instead of
				List&lt;IResource&gt;
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				HAPI parsers now use field access to get/set values instead of method accessors and mutators.
				This should give a small performance boost.
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				JSON parser encodes resource references incorrectly, using the name "resource" instead
				of the name "reference" for the actual reference. Thanks to
				Ricky Nguyen for reporting and tracking down the issue!
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Rename NotImpementedException to NotImplementedException (to correct typo)
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Server setUseBrowserFriendlyContentType setting also respected for errors (e.g. OperationOutcome with 4xx/5xx status)
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Fix performance issue in date/time datatypes where pattern matchers were not static
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Server now gives a more helpful error message if a @Read method has a search parameter (which is invalid, but
				previously lead to a very unhelpful error message). Thanks to Tahura Chaudhry of UHN for reporting!
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Resource of type "List" failed to parse from a bundle correctly. Thanks to David Hay of Orion Health 
				for reporting!
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				QuantityParam correctly encodes approximate (~) prefix to values
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="14">
				If a server defines a method with parameter "_id", incoming search requests for that method may
				get delegated to the wrong method. Thanks to Neal Acharya for reporting! 
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				SecurityEvent.Object structural element has been renamed to 
				SecurityEvent.ObjectElement to avoid conflicting names with the 
				java Object class. Thanks to Laurie Macdougall-Sookraj of UHN for
				reporting! 
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Text/narrative blocks that were created with a non-empty
				namespace prefix (e.g. &lt;xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="..."&gt;...&lt;/xhtml:div&gt;)
				failed to encode correctly (prefix was missing in encoded resource)				
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Resource references previously encoded their children (display and reference)
				in the wrong order so references with both would fail schema validation.
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				SecurityEvent resource's enums now use friendly enum names instead of the unfriendly
				numeric code values. Thanks to Laurie MacDougall-Sookraj of UHN for the
				suggestion!
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="0.5" date="2014-07-30">
			<action type="add">
				HAPI has a number of RESTful method parameter types that have similar but not identical
				purposes and confusing names. A cleanup has been undertaken to clean this up.
				This means that a number of existing classes
				have been deprocated in favour of new naming schemes.
				<![CDATA[<br/><br/>]]>
				All annotation-based clients and all server search method parameters are now named
				(type)Param, for example: StringParam, TokenParam, etc.
				<![CDATA[<br/><br/>]]>
				All generic/fluent client method parameters are now named
				(type)ClientParam, for example: StringClientParam, TokenClientParam, etc.
				<![CDATA[<br/><br/>]]>
				All renamed classes have been retained and deprocated, so this change should not cause any issues
				for existing applications but those applications should be refactored to use the 
				new parameters when possible.
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Allow server methods to return wildcard generic types (e.g. List&lt;? extends IResource&gt;)
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Search parameters are not properly escaped and unescaped. E.g. for a token parameter such as
				"&amp;identifier=system|codepart1\|codepart2"
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Add support for OPTIONS verb (which returns the server conformance statement)
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Add support for CORS headers in server
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Bump SLF4j dependency to latest version (1.7.7)
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Add interceptor framework for clients (annotation based and generic), and add interceptors
				for configurable logging, capturing requests and responses, and HTTP basic auth.
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Transaction client invocations with XML encoding were using the wrong content type ("application/xml+fhir" instead 
				of the correct "application/atom+xml"). Thanks to David Hay of Orion Health for surfacing this one!
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Bundle entries now support a link type of "search". Thanks to David Hay for the suggestion!
			</action>
			<action type="add" issue="1">
				 If a client receives a non 2xx response (e.g. HTTP 500) and the response body is a text/plain message or
				 an OperationOutcome resource, include the message in the exception message so that it will be 
				 more conveniently displayed in logs and other places. Thanks to Neal Acharya for the suggestion! 
			</action>
			<action type="add" issue="2">
				 Read invocations in the client now process the "Content-Location" header and use it to 
				 populate the ID of the returned resource. Thanks to Neal Acharya for the suggestion!
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="3">
				Fix issue where vread invocations on server incorrectly get routed to instance history method if one is 
				defined. Thanks to Neal Acharya from UHN for surfacing this one! 
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Binary reads on a server not include the Content-Disposition header, to prevent HTML in binary 
				blobs from being used for nefarious purposes. See
				<![CDATA[<a href="http://gforge.hl7.org/gf/project/fhir/tracker/?action=TrackerItemEdit&tracker_id=677&tracker_item_id=3298">FHIR Tracker Bug 3298</a>]]>
				for more information.
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Support has been added for using an HTTP proxy for outgoing requests.
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Fix: Primitive extensions declared against custom resource types 
				are encoded even if they have no value. Thanks to David Hay of Orion for
				reporting this!
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Fix: RESTful server deployed to a location where the URL to access it contained a
				space (e.g. a WAR file with a space in the name) failed to work correctly.
				Thanks to David Hay of Orion for reporting this!
			</action>
        </release>			
		<release version="0.4" date="2014-07-13">
			<action type="add">
				<![CDATA[<b>BREAKING CHANGE:</b>]]>: IdDt has been modified so that it 
				contains a partial or complete resource identity. Previously it contained
				only the simple alphanumeric id of the resource (the part at the end of the "read" URL for
				that resource) but it can now contain a complete URL or even a partial URL (e.g. "Patient/123")
				and can optionally contain a version (e.g. "Patient/123/_history/456"). New methods have
				been added to this datatype which provide just the numeric portion. See the JavaDoc
				for more information. 
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				<![CDATA[<b>API CHANGE:</b>]]>: Most elements in the HAPI FHIR model contain
				a getId() and setId() method. This method is confusing because it is only actually used
				for IDREF elements (which are rare) but its name makes it easy to confuse with more
				important identifiers. For this reason, these methods have been deprocated and replaced with
				get/setElementSpecificId() methods. The old methods will be removed at some point. Resource
				types are unchanged and retain their get/setId methods.
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Allow use of QuantityDt as a service parameter to support the "quantity" type. Previously
				QuantityDt did not implement IQueryParameterType so it was not valid, and there was no way to
				support quantity search parameters on the server (e.g. Observation.value-quantity)
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Introduce StringParameter type which can be used as a RESTful operation search parameter
				type. StringParameter allows ":exact" matches to be specified in clients, and handled in servers.
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Parsers (XML/JSON) now support deleted entries in bundles
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Transaction method now supported in servers
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Support for Binary resources added (in servers, clients, parsers, etc.)
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Support for Query resources fixed (in parser)
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Nested contained resources (e.g. encoding a resource with a contained resource that itself contains a resource)
				now parse and encode correctly, meaning that all contained resources are placed in the "contained" element
				of the root resource, and the parser looks in the root resource for all container levels when stitching
				contained resources back together.
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Server methods with @Include parameter would sometimes fail when no _include was actually
				specified in query strings.
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Client requests for IdentifierDt types (such as Patient.identifier) did not create the correct
				query string if the system is null.
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Add support for paging responses from RESTful servers.
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Don't fail on narrative blocks in JSON resources with only an XML declaration but no content (these are
				produced by the Health Intersections server) 
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Server now automatically compresses responses if the client indicates support 
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Server failed to support optional parameters when type is String and :exact qualifier is used 
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Read method in client correctly populated resource ID in returned object 
			</action>
			<action type="add">
				Support added for deleted-entry by/name, by/email, and comment from Tombstones spec
			</action>
        </release>			
		<release version="0.3" date="2014-04-12" description="This release corrects lots of bugs and introduces the fluent client mode">
        </release>			
	</body>
</document>
