<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">

	<properties>
		<title>Server Security</title>
	</properties>

	<body>

		<!-- The body of the document contains a number of sections -->
		<section name="Server Security">

			<p>
				Security is a complex topic which goes far beyond the scope of HAPI FHIR.
				HAPI does provide mechanisms which can be used to implement security in
				your server however.
			</p>
			
			<p>
				Because HAPI FHIR's REST server is based on the Servlet API, you may use any
				security mechanism which works in that environment. Some serlvet containers
				may provide security layers you can plug into. The rest of this page
				does not explore that method, but rather looks at HAPI FHIR hooks that can
				be used to implement FHIR specific security.
			</p>
			
			<subsection name="Authentication vs Authorization">
			
				<p>
					Background reading: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Authentication">Wikipedia - Authentication</a>
				</p>
				<p>
					Server security is divided into two topics:
				</p>
				<ul>
					<li>
						<b>Authentication (AuthN):</b> Is verifying that the user is who they say they 
						are. This is typically accomplished by testing a username/password in the request,
						or by checking a "bearer token" in the request.
					</li>
					<li>
						<b>Authorization (AuthZ):</b> Is verifying that the user is allowed to perform 
						the given action. For example, in a FHIR application you might use AuthN to test that
						the user making a request to the FHIR server is allowed to access the server, but
						that test might determine that the requesting user is not permitted to perform
						write operations and therefore block a FHIR <code>create</code> operation. This is
						AuthN and AuthZ in action.
					</li>
				</ul>
				
			</subsection>
			
		</section>
		
		<section name="Authentication Interceptors">
		
			<p>
				The <a href="./doc_rest_server_interceptor.html">Server Interceptor</a>
				framework can provide an easy way to test for credentials. The following
				example shows a simple interceptor which tests for HTTP Basic Auth.
			</p>
			
			<macro name="snippet">
				<param name="id" value="basicAuthInterceptor" />
				<param name="file" value="examples/src/main/java/example/SecurityInterceptors.java" />
			</macro>
			
		</section>
		
		<section name="Authorization Interceptor">
			
			<p>
				HAPI FHIR 1.5 introduced a new interceptor, the
				<a href="./apidocs/ca/uhn/fhir/rest/server/interceptor/auth/AuthorizationInterceptor.html">AuthorizationInterceptor</a>.
			</p>
			<p>
				This interceptor can help with the complicated task of determining whether a user
				has the appropriate permission to perform a given task on a FHIR server. This is
				done by declaring
			</p>
						
		</section>
		
	</body>

</document>
