<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">

	<properties>
		<title>FHIR DSTU2 Support</title>
		<author email="jamesagnew@users.sourceforge.net">James Agnew</author>
	</properties>

	<body>

		<section name="Working with DSTU2">

			<p>
				Although DSTU2 has not yet been balloted and finalized by HL7, 
				there are several proposed changes which have been incorporated
				into the current 
				<a href="http://hl7-fhir.github.io/">Continuous Integration Builds</a>
				of the FHIR specification itself and many (if not most) of these changes will 
				end up in the final DSTU2 specification which is expected to be released 
				in mid-2015.
			</p>
			<p>
				The most interesting changes to DSTU2 include:
			</p>
			<ul>
				<li>
					New 
					<a href="http://hl7-fhir.github.io/resource.html">"id" and "meta"</a>
					elements which are present on all resources and explicitly state the resource's
					ID, version, tags, and a few other things. All of these concepts had previously
					existed in FHIR but were not a part of the resource body itself (rather they lived
					in URLs and HTTP headers outside of the payload)
				</li>
				<li>
					A new 
					<a href="http://hl7-fhir.github.io/bundle.html">Bundle</a> 
					format which is no longer based on Atom. The new format does resemble the
					Atom format so it will not be unfamiliar to anyone who is used to DSTU1 bundles
					but it has a few differences. On a conceptual level FHIR now thinks of Bundles as
					resources themselves, so the new bundle also gains the meta element described above.  
				</li>
				<li>
					<strike>In <a href="http://hl7-fhir.github.io/json.html">JSON encoding</a>, the 
					encoding of extensions has changed a bit, so that extensions on non-primitive
					elements now appear with the extension URL as the JSON key, instead of being 
					a value in an object called "extension". See the JSON documentation to see how
					this new style looks.</strike> This change was reverted by HL7.
				</li>
				<li>
					A number of new resources have been added, and some existing resources have changed.
					One particularly visible (and non-backwards-compatible) change is that 
					Patient.gender has changed from a CodeableConcept to a Code. While this new type
					is much more intuitive (having multiple codings attached to a single gender field is
					confusing) it does mean that existing DSTU1 Patient resources will not parse correctly 
					as DSTU2 resources if they include a gender.
				</li>
			</ul>
			
			<subsection name="Supporting DSTU2 In your Applications">
				
				<p>
					As of HAPI FHIR 0.9, support for DSTU2 has been added to the library. Although upgrading
					existing applications from DSTU1 to DSTU2 will not be painless, we have
					tried as much as possible to make it easy.
				</p>
				
				<p>
					First, support for DSTU2 capabilities has been added in a second optional dependency JAR which
					you must add to your classpath. This JAR is called <code>hapi-structures-dstu2-[version].jar</code>.
					See the <a href="./download.html">download page</a> for information on adding this JAR.
				</p>
				
				<p>
					The FHIR version you are targeting is a property of the 
					<a href="http://jamesagnew.github.io/hapi-fhir/apidocs/ca/uhn/fhir/context/FhirContext.html">FhirContext</a>.
					This means that if you use a FhirContext instance that is configured for DSTU2, any parsers, clients,
					servers, etc. which use that context will be operating in DSTU2 mode.
				</p>

				<p>
					To create a DSTU2 context, simply use the "forDstu2" factory method on the FhirContext class:
				</p>
				
				<macro name="snippet">
					<param name="id" value="context" />
					<param name="file" value="examples/src/main/java/example/Dstu2Examples.java" />
				</macro>
				
			</subsection>
			
			<subsection name="DSTU2 Servers">
				
				<p>
					To support DSTU2 in your server, simply set the FhirContext in the server to be
					one configured for DSTU2. 
				</p>
				
				<macro name="snippet">
					<param name="id" value="server" />
					<param name="file" value="examples/src/main/java/example/Dstu2Examples.java" />
				</macro>
				
				<p>
					Note that it is possible to share your resource provider classes between 
					servers supporting DSTU1 and servers supporting DSTU2 (including in the same WAR
					instance on the same web server). This should make the process of upgrading your
					server to the latest version of FHIR a bit easier.
				</p>
				
			</subsection>

		</section>
		
	</body>

</document>
